Guide to the Montana Constitutional Convention (1884) Records 1884-
Montana Historical Society
Montana Constitutional Convention (1884) Records
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 147
Montana Constitutional Convention (1884)
1.75 linear feet of shelf space
These Montana Constitutional Convention records (1884) consist of minutes, shorthand records and transcriptions of daily proceedings, committee reports, oaths of office, motions, petitions, resolutions, amendments, membership cards, payrolls, attendance lists, payrolls, etc. (Same as State Microfilm 39.)
The Territory of Montana was created by the U.S. Congress on May 26, 1864. In 1866 a constitution was written by Montana residents, but it was never submitted to Congress. Then, in 1883, the Thirteenth Legislative Assembly of the Territory of Montana authorized an election in November 1883 to select delegates to attend a constitutional convention in Helena the following January. Delegates were elected from existing counties and judicial districts. William A. Clark was elected president of the convention. The 1884 Constitution was approved by popular vote of territorial residents. However, this constitution did not receive approval of the U.S. Congress because the majority in Congress belonged to the Republican Party and the voters of Montana Territory had elected primarily Democratic officials. On February 22, 1889, President Grover Cleveland signed enabling legislation known as the Omnibus Statehood Bill providing for constitutional conventions to be called on July 4, 1889, in Montana, Washington, and North and South Dakota territories. The 1889 Constitution, based largely on the earlier effort in 1884, was approved by Congress and Montana became the forty-first state on November 8, 1889.
The records of the 1884 Constitutional Convention include payrolls for convention members and employees; attendance lists; minute book of daily sessions (transcribed); original minutes of daily sessions (includes some correspondence, motions, resolutions, amendments, and committee reports); daily proceedings taken in Pittman shorthand arranged by day; transcriptions of proceedings arranged by day; committee reports; oaths of office; membership cards; petitions; and rules, motions, amendments, and resolutions.
The collection is arranged by series
The collection is also available on Microfilm (MHS call number SMF 39).
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Constitutional conventions--Montana
Montana--Politics and government
Montana; Government and politics
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Minutes
  - Minute book, 1884 January-February (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Minutes: 1st-27th days [3rd, 7th, 14th, 21st days missing; 23rd day includes speech by Joseph K. Toole], 1884 January-February (Box-folder 1 / 2-18)
- Proceedings
  - Proceedings: 1st-27th days [7th, 14th, 21st days missing; includes stenographer's certificate of accuracy, May 1884], 1884 January-February (Box-folder 1 / 19-22)
  - Shorthand notes of proceedings: 1st-5th days [4th day missing], 1884 January 14-18 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
  - Shorthand notes of proceedings: 8th-20th days [14th day missing], 1884 January 21-February 2 (Box-folder 2 / 1-9)
  - Shorthand notes of proceedings: 22nd-27th days, 1884 February 4-9 (Box-folder 3 / 1-3)
- Reports
  - Committee reports (includes Committee on Executive Departments; proposal by Martin Maginnis to substitute "president" for "governor" in constitution; proposal by Joseph K. Toole re taxation; Committee on Agriculture, Manufactures, Commerce, and Emigration; resolution to Congress to grant 160,000 acres to Montana for erecting state buildings and colleges, and for improvements on the Missouri, Yellowstone, and Clark Fork rivers), 1884 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
- Miscellany
  - Oaths of office, 1884 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Order of business and standing committee membership cards, 1884 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Payroll and attendance records, 1884 (Box-folder OvFd / 1)
  - Petitions (re separation of church and state, banning alcohol production and distribution, and equal taxation of property), 1884 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Rules, motions, amendments, and articles, 1884 (Box-folder 3 / 8)